Guide to the Frederick T. Bent papers, [ca. 1947]-1987.
Bent, Frederick T. papers, [ca. 1947]-1987
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Frederick T. Bent papers, [ca. 1947]-1987.
26-2-2343
Frederick T. Bent, 1921-1987.
2.6 cubic ft.
Papers, outlines, class notes, correspondence, articles, speeches, reports.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The majority of Bent's papers consist of outlines, class notes, and class lists relating to courses he taught in politics, international relations, administrative law, management, agricultural and economic development.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of public administration.
Frederick T. Bent graduated from Ohio State University in 1943, and received his M.A. in 1947 and Ph.D. in 1954 from the University of Chicago. He studied political science and minored in industrial relations. His teaching positions include: assistant and later associate professor, American University of Beirut (1951-55), where he helped establish the school's first public administration program; assistant professor of political science, Coe College, Cedar Rapids, Iowa (1955-1956) and University of Pennsylvania (1956-1958); associate professor of public administration, Cornell University Graduate School of Management (1958-1987). Between 1962 and 1965, he taught at Middle East Technical University in Ankara, Turkey. Bent was a consultant to several Middle Eastern governments and universities, and worked with the U.S. Agency for International Development and the Ford Foundation. He advised the government of Bahrain on public administration in 1973 and was director of The American University of Beirut's School of Management from 1978 to 1981. He was also active in local politics in Ithaca and Lansing, New York, seving as chairman of the Liberal Party of Tompkins County and the Tompkins County Social Planning Council.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The majority of Bent's papers consist of outlines, class notes, and class lists relating to courses he taught in politics, international relations, administrative law, management, agricultural and economic development, and other subjects at Cornell in the 1970s and 1980s; correspondence and memoranda pertaining to the Graduate School of Management; drafts of Bent's writings, including articles and THE TURKISH HIGHER CIVIC SERVICE; speeches on terrorism, Lebanon, and U.S./Middle East policies; correspondence, reports, and other materials concerning Bent's interest in the American University of Beirut, Kuwait University, Middle East Technical University, Turkey, Lebanon, and Bahrain; notes on Ithaca, New York, government; and materials on his consulting work.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bent, Frederick T., 1921-1987.; American University of Beirut.; Cornell University. Graduate School of Management.; Jåami°at al-Kuwayt.; Orta Doægu Teknik èUniversitesi (Ankara, Turkey)
Titles:
The Turkish higher civil service.
Subjects:
Developing countries--Middle East.; Industrial management.; International relations.; Political science--Study and teaching.; Terrorism--Middle East.; College teachers.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Lebanon--Politics and government.; Middle East--Economic conditions.; Middle East--Foreign relations.; Middle East--Politics and government.; Middle East--Study and teaching.; Turkey--Politics and government.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Introduction to Comparative International Management, NBA 585, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- International and Comparative Management, NBA, Spring, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- International and Comparative Management, NBA 585 (China's Economy), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- International and Comparative Management, NCE 508 (Middle East Management), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Management in Israel, The Arab Nations, and the LCD's: A Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 5)
- International and Comparative Management, NCE 508, Spring, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- International and Comparative Management, NBA 585. Outline, Class Role and Objectives. Spring, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- International and Comparative Management, NBA 585. Japanese Management. Class lists fron Spring Term, Student Comments, Reserve Reading Lists, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- National Journal Citations, 191980's (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Public Administration Colloquium (NPA 518). Schedule of Speakers/Names, etc., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Introduction to Public Administration Colloquium (NPA 519), 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Municipal Trade Unions for NPA 518, Nov. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- New York City Budget for NPA 518, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- New Federalism - Stuart Butler of the Heritage Foundation, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- National Urban Coalition, Social Impact of President Reagen's Urban Policy for NPA 519, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- International Government Relations for NPA 518, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Dr. E.S. Savas, Assistant Secretary for Policy and Research, Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Public Affairs Colloquium, NBA 518, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Administrative Law and Management, NPA 513, Class Roll and Course Material, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Control Data Corporation (City Venture Corporation) NPA 518, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Administrative Law and Management, Items for NPA 573, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Administrative Law and Management, NPA 513. Adminstrative Process, Delegation, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Administrative Law and Management, NPA 513. Institutional Decisions, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Administrative Law and Management, NPA 513. Institutional Decisions, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Administrative Law and Management, NPA 513. Informational Procedures, Reviewability (Box 1, Folder 25)
- The Conduct of Public Affairs I (NPP 500), Exemption Exam, Fall 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Seminar in Public Systems (NPA 512), Introduction Analysis (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Seminars in Public Systems, NPA 512, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- American Red Cross - NPA 512 (Class Report), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- City Government Projects, NPA 512, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Challenge Industries, NPA 512, 191983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Ithaca Festival Project for NPA 512 (Public Systems Analysis) (Box 1, Folder 32)
- George Junior Republic proposed study for NPA 512 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Tompkins County Services Reports, NPA 512 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Ithaca City School District Projects for NPA 512 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Administration of Agriculture and Rural Development, NCE 514 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Environment for International Buisness: The Middle East, Course Enrollment, Outline, NBA 583 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Economic Environment, Political Stability: The Middle East, NBA 583 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- An Introduction to Saudi Arabia; Doing Buisness in Saudi Arabia, NBA 583 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Contemporary Policies and Economic Environment of Egypt, CAU, July 1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Politics and Development in the Arabian Gulf, NCE 506 (outline), Fall 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Politics and Development in the Arabian Gulf, NCE 506. Outlines, Class Lists, Spring 1982 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- L'Ecole Centrale (Paris), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Adam Benado, Robert Friedman, Mohammad Ilyas, Bassam Camadan (graduate students), 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- AACBS Workshop for Internationalizing the Buisness School Curriculum, NYC, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- AACBS - American Assembly of Collegiate Schools of Buisness Symposium on "How Buisness Deals with Washington", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Buisness School Internships, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Institute of International Education, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Guest Lecturer, Dr. Massoud Ahari of Iran, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter I) (Box 1, Folder 50)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter II) (Box 1, Folder 51)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter III) (Box 1, Folder 52)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter IV) (Box 1, Folder 53)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter V) (Box 1, Folder 54)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter VI, VII, VIII) (Box 1, Folder 55)
- The Turkish Higher Civil Service, by Frederick T. Bent (Chapter IX) (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Mutinational Firms and Developing Economy: The Experience of Educador (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Rejected Article: "Foreign Service and Foreign Aid: Conflict or Cooperation?", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Columbia Journal of World Buisness, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Letters to Officals at Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey, May 1966-July 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- C.U. Middle East Technical University Research Project: The Turkish Public Service, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Public Administration Review, June 1970-Dec. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Outline of a Book to be Edited by James. A. Socnat. (Including list of potential contributors), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Professor Bent's Consulting, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Agency for International Development; F.T.B.'s Assignment in Beirut, Lebanon, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Blue Ribbon Panel for City of Ithaca's Charter and Code Examinations, June 1982-Aug. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Blue Ribbon Panel - City of Ithaca, Sept. 1983-Oct. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Blue Ribbon Panel - City of Ithaca, Nov. 1983-Dec. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Public Management Program, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Kuwait University, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Canadian Studies in the U.S., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Graduate School of Management Dean's Memos, 1981; 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Letters and Memos re James A. Purdy, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Armed Conflict and Society Course, Fall 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Speeches on Terrorism, Fall 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Speech - "Dead End: USA/Middle East Policies - Some Solutions", Apr. 15, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Cornell Radio Program, Aug. 5, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- BPA Alumni Talk, Apr. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- BPA Talk: "Working in the Lebanon/Gulf Area", Nov. 1981; May 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Bahrain-Ford Foundation, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Bahrain Planning Document, 1974-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Bahrain Planning Document (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Bahrain Customs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Bahrain Customs Project, June 1977-July 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Management Training in Bahrain (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Bahrain - Notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Bahrain - Notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Bahrain - Notes (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Bahrain - Transport, Communications, Traffic (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Bahrain - Report on Planning for Social Development, by Walter James, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Inventory and Assessment of Employement-orientated Human Resources Development Programs in the Gulf Area, by James A. Socknat, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- American University of Beirut: (GPDA 311) Introduction to the Development Administration held at the Graduate Program in Development Administration, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- American University of Beirut: (GPDA 316) Implementation of National Plans held at the Graduate Program in Development Administration, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- To the Arab World for the International Executive Service Corps by Deane W. Malott. Part I (Box 3, Folder 15)
- To the Arab World for the International Executive Service Corps by Deane W. Malott. Part II (Box 3, Folder 16)